In this video, we'll be taking a look at if else.
I'll be discussing a flow control using if else with operators and statement initialization.
So first, we need to talk about flow control.
Program code executes line by line, and flow control is a way to interrupt this line by
line process.
We can have different lines of code that can be executed based on different conditions.
And these conditions are programmer defined, and you can make as many conditions as you need
in order to get your program to run and the job completed.
So this is what an if and an if else looks like.
We have the if keyword, and then some kind of condition.
The condition must evaluate to either true or false.
If it's true, code will be executed inside this block.
And so you can do whatever you want in here.
Here we have an if else.
So same as above, we have if some condition.
We'll do some code here if that's true.
If it's false, else, then we'll do something else in here.
So the first block is the true's condition.
And the else block is the false condition.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here we have if some username, which will be string, if it's not equal to a blank input.
So there is a name, then we'll process it.
And if the if the input is blank, then we'll display some kind of error message.
And on the bottom, we're just doing something similar without the else block.
So we only are interested in processing the username, and we don't do anything else on the bottom example.
It's also possible to nest else ifs.
So what we're doing here is we're checking someone's age.
So this entire thing here is going to evaluate to either true or false.
Remember that relational operators determine true or false.
So if somebody's age is greater than or equal to 21, if that's true,
then we'll permit their entry to a venue.
If this is false, we're going to go down to the next block here.
So else, we use the keyword if again.
So else if we have parental approval, and if that happens to be true,
then we'll permit entry again.
So if that's true, that'll be executed.
If this one is false, and this one is false, then finally,
this last block will get executed, and we'll have a some kind of code where they cannot enter the venue.
You can have as many else if blocks as you want for
whatever conditions you're trying to test for.
So you can have one, you could have none, you can have five or six, you can have 20.
All of that's OK.
Now let's take a look at how we can use if with some logical operators.
Here we have if has ticket, and ticket valid.
So this has to be true, and this has to be true, then we'll execute the code here in this block.
In this example here, we have if the funds are greater than the cost.
So this whole thing will evaluate either two or false, and the account is active.
So if that's true, and this is true, then we'll enter into this block here.
In this third example, if we're either using a debit card or
using a credit card, then we'll enter this block.
Since we're using or either one of these can be false.
So if this is false, that's OK, and if this is true, we'll so enter.
If both of these are false, then we won't execute the code here.
So as long as one thing is true, with all of these expressions,
then we'll be able to do see if block here.
And finally here at the bottom, we have a negation.
So if the quiz is not complete, then we're going to display an incomplete submission morning.
This quiz complete here, that's going to be a Boolean.
So that's either going to be true or false.
We can also use if statements with functions.
So here we have our if keyword, and we're calling the temperature function of the freezer.
So we're checking the temperature on a freezer.
And if that temperature is greater than zero, we'll display an alert.
And we can use multiple functions here.
So if the temp in the freezer is greater than the preferred temp in the freezer,
then we can display an alert as well.
And just like with the previous slides, you can use or an end to combine multiple
different function calls.
Go has a feature called statement initialization.
And what this allows us to do is allows us to create a variable and
do a comparison at the same time.
So here in this first example, we're creating the variable named I using the create
and assign operator, and we're sending it to the value of five.
We then have a semicolon and we can do a logic check.
So here we're creating I assign it to five.
We then check to see if I is less than 10.
If this evaluates to true, then the block will be executed.
If this evaluates to false, then we'll go down into the else block and
do something else in the second example.
We're using the rank keyword and we're getting the user rank function.
And this rank function will determine if they're an admin or user or guest.
If rank happens to be admin, then we'll be able to do administrative things here.
If the rank is manager, then they can do manager things.
And finally, at the bottom, we'll display an error message because for
this particular functionality, they're not able to do anything unless they're an
admin or a manager.
Remember with statement initialization, we need to have the if keyword followed
by our initialization statement, a semicolon, and then our comparison at the end.
The comparison should always refer to the variable that you created in the
initialization statement.
When you do so, you'll be able to access this variable within this block.
Something closely related to control flow is an early return.
An early return is simply using the if statement to validate some data.
When the data is validated, you're able to continue with the function.
If the data fails validation, you return early from the function.
You want to do this because it maximizes performance.
And once you've checked all the data, you're able to use it without having any issues.
This leads to cleaner code and reduces the amount of bugs that you have in your
program.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here we have a get session function and it returns a session token or an error.
The first thing we want to do is use if to check the error.
So if the error is not nil, remember that nil is nothing.
So if it's not nothing, meaning we do have some kind of error, then we'll
return immediately out of the function.
That's because this token will not be valid because some kind of error occurred.
The same thing down here with get cart.
So here we use our existing token in our get cart function.
And if that's successful, then we get a cart.
However, if we have an error, we need to check that.
And if we get an error back, then we should return from the function.
If both of the error from get session and get cart, if both of those are nil,
it will end up down here at the bottom and will have valid token data and
valid cart data, this makes it okay to process a shopping cart.
This if air is not equal to nil, we'll see that a lot in your go code.
Because when functions return an error, you always need to check to see if
that error value exists.
And if it does, you want to return from the function.
And you can also perform logging in here if you like.
Let's recap.
Flow controls a way to change which lines of code execute.
If else can be used to conditionally execute code.
And we can also use else if for testing multiple different conditions.
If statements can be used with return values from function calls and
logical inequality operators can also be used with if statements.
Statement initialization allows for a variable to be created and tested within
the scope of an if else block.
And early returns should always be used when possible for
efficiency and code clarity.